So he says this
.  "I treat my mind
like a wild animal to be conquered
. Hearing your talk about the 'wild mind'
makes me think that.
Yes. Rather than being consumed by the specific emotions the mind emits
, I fight it as if it were a separate enemy
.
However, fighting the mind as a separate enemy
creates a painful split within me
. That is the feeling. How
can I continue practicing becoming someone who controls and trains their mind without getting exhausted in this ceaseless inner battle?"
Well, you might feel a sense of division
.  However, that
sense of division does not arise from you trying to fight wild animals
.  It happens because the animal itself is
wild .  Of course, if you don't try to train the dog, you will
.  Of course, if you don't try to train the dog, you will
never know how wild it was.
If you always do exactly what the dog wants, it will think, "It's
okay. We're doing well.
"  And
then, if you
do not give the animal what it wants, you
will realize how different it is in its condition.  Of course, the natural immediate
reaction is,
"It's because I tried to force them.
"
However, the statement "No, it is
because the animal was not trained"
fits perfectly.  It is simply that
forcing training or restraint
revealed their wild nature
.  There is no other way
.  Of course, if it is too difficult
, you may need to proceed a bit more slowly and gradually
.  But again
, if you leave animals to their wild instincts, you
cannot tame them.  That
won't work.  If you do that,
all the effort you have put in so far will simply go to
waste.
Yes, you should
n't just let them escape.
So, if you get tired, it is
okay to slow down, but you
must maintain your direction.    It will
feel like it is on fire
.  It's like training for something rough
.  Then, when that feeling subsides, it wo
n't flare up anymore.  And you wo
n't need to train anymore
.  So there are
no problems.  However, if the standard is
'if I feel something strange while doing something
, I must
never do that thing,'
that could be a problem.
Yes, yes, yes.
No, that is a problem.  If
that is the standard, you will
give up on training soon
.  The mind comes to think, 'I just
want to become one with the minds.'    hmm.
Just go with the flow and do as you
please.  You will feel
good.  yes.  But until I can
no longer do that.  And then
you will pay the price
.  Because there is
no one there.  Yes, it
feels like I have to force my thoughts, my stupid thoughts, onto my mind.  It sounds a bit harsh, doesn't it?
It's a bit cruel.
But sometimes you have to be cruel
.  Hmm, once again, define
cruelty .  For example, is it cruel to
.  For example, is it cruel to
remove food stuck in a baby's throat
?  Your skin could tear
and get wounded
.  Is that cruel?
Even thinking rationally, can it be
called cruel?  He said,
"No, saving lives is more important
."  They would probably say that
.  The same goes for this
.  If you cannot see the bigger picture
, the act of inflicting pain, whether direct or indirect, becomes cruel
, and then you can never
be free.  We
need a bigger picture.  Because it is bound to be painful from the start
.  Saying "no" to desire is also
painful.  However, you must do so on your own before the situation takes over you
.
Otherwise, it will be too late to train your mind
.  As I
mentioned in my previous lecture, change must
come from within yourself and should not be swayed by circumstances
.
Otherwise, anyone imprisoned or
confined to a solitary cell would have
automatically become an Arhat
.  Because once you have so
much taken away from them,
"No."  That is
because I have that thought.  You must convey
such a message to the heart, not to the world
.  I can't have this
.  You can have that.
No, no, no.  I am
making that decision because I have figured out what needs to be tamed and trained, and where the hidden tendencies lie behind it.